National Captive Nations Committee Collection
National Captive Nations Committee Collection
1960-1982
National Captive Nations Committee.
3 linear ft.
Correspondence, published material, news releases, clippings (information artifacts), photographs, printed material, books relating to the anti-Communist National Captive Nations Committee and to its chairman Lev Dobriansky.
2709009
Biographical History
The National Captive Nations Committee is a Washington, D.C.-based anti-Communism advocacy group created in 1959 by Public Law 86-90 under President Dwight D. Eisenhower. PL 86-90 compels every President of the United States to proclaim the third week of July of each year as Captive Nations Week, as commemoration to the "captive nations" (those with Communist governments). The NCNC is a watershed organization which acts as a coordinator for smaller, localized organizations including the Americans for the Freedom of Captive Nations of Los Angeles, California and the Washington Captive Nations Committee of Washington, D.C.. The NCNC distributes publications throughout the year but their peak activity is in July during the observance of Captive Nations Week.
Dr. Lev E. Dobriansky (1918-2008), a professor of Economics at Georgetown University, was the chairman of the NCNC, having written the Captive Nations Week Resolution which became PL 86-90 and gave rise to the committee. Born in New York City to Ukrainian immigrant parents, he was also the president of the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America (UCCA) and very active in Ukrainian independence. He contributed to the Shevchenko Monument Resolution, leading to the erection of a statue for the 19th century Ukrainian freedom fighter in Washington, D.C.. He had years of correspondence with Dr. Ku Cheng-kang, honorary chairman of the World Anti-Communist League (WACL). Dobriansky was also affiliated with the American Council for World Freedom (ACWF) and a number of other anti-Communist (particularly anti-Soviet) organizations and activists. Dobriansky was appointed Ambassador to the Bahamas between 1982 and 1986 by President Reagan. He retired from Georgetown in 1987.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The National Captive Nations Committee Collection consists of correspondence (both personal and professional), published material, news releases, clippings, photographs, printed material, and books. Most of the material is about the Captive Nations movement, but there is also a large amount of material that is more broadly anti-Communist and not explicitly pertaining to the NCNC. Dobriansky, when donating the NCNC collection, included material like the program to a conference called "The United States and China after Mao," an official copy of the presidential proclamation of Human Rights in 1973, and personal condolences to George Meany's widow.
A large portion of the collection directly relates to the observance of Captive Nations Week between 1960 and 1981, although the material is inconsistent in quantity and format from year to year. There are many clippings from the Congressional Record that document the speeches by Representatives who supported NCNC and the Captive Nations Week. There are also copies of the mass distributed letters written by Dobriansky and sent to the President, Congressmen, Senators, Governors, Mayors, and other figures asking that they officially proclaim Captive Nations Week. The collection includes responses from those political figures. The politicians most active in the NCNC's work were Daniel Flood, Edward Derwinski and Samuel Stratton. Some Captive Nation Week folders have clippings of editorials and announcement of planned events as well as memorabilia, like programs and invitations from Captive Nation Week events from around the world. Of interest may be Captive Nations Week 1977, when President Jimmy Carter was conspicuously late with his proclamation and did not issue it until mid-week, raising much ire within the NCNC.
Dobriansky repeatedly tried throughout the 1960s and 1970s to get a Special Committee on the Captive Nations created in Congress. Multiple resolutions were drafted to this effect and there are many Congressional Record pages with speeches by Representatives Flood and Derwinski in support of this effort but they were unsuccessful.
Throughout the time span of this collection, Dr. Dobriansky corresponded regularly with Dr. Ku Chang-keng (Gu Zhenggang) of Taiwan, honorary chairman of the World Anti-Communist League (WACL) and member of the Asian People's Anti-Communist League (APACL). The letters between these two men often discuss the plans for Captive Nations Week events, World Freedom Day events, or WACL conferences. Dobriansky would help Ku arrange for American politicians to speak at events in Taiwan in support of Republic of China there, including Jack Kemp, Jesse Helms, and Strom Thurmond. The collection includes memorabilia from some of those events.
The collection includes many pamphlets and correspondence from Fred Schlafly, president of the American Council for World Freedom (ACWF) and his wife, Phyllis Schlafly, who eventually joined the NCNC board of directors. Phyllis Schlafly produced the Phyllis Schlafly Report, a conservative, self-published periodical. One issue included in this collection is entitled "What's Wrong with 'Equal Rights' for Women?" with subheadings including "The Financial Benefits of Chivalry," "The Right NOT To Take A Job," and "The Fraud of The Equal Rights Amendment."
There are also many publications by Dobriansky in the collection. He was a prolific writer and contributed to the Ukrainian Quarterly on a frequent basis throughout the 1960s and 1970s. This collection includes two decades worth of Dobriansky's efforts with regard to Ukraine, specifically about religion in Ukraine and the observation of Ukrainian Independence Day. Additionally, there are issues of The Ukrainian Bulletin which mention the Captive Nations movement or cite Dobriansky.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is alphabetized by subject. The subject folders are arranged chronologically with the exception of the four folders, General Correspondence and Dobriansky- Correspondence: A-G, H-N and O-Z, which are alphabetized by the last name of the sender. In the Captive Nations Week folders, where there is a large amount of clippings from the Congressional Record, those Congressional Record pages are foldered separately from and immediately before the rest of the material for that Captive Nations Week.
Related Material
The Special Collections Research Center has a large number of collections about the Communist movement in America. Please refer to for a complete listing. For additional anti-Communist material, see also the
George S. Schuyler Papers
.
Separated Material
Some items have been removed and sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please search for "Gift of Lev Dobriansky" to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Dobriansky, Lev E.; Gu, Zhenggang, 1901-; National Captive Nations Committee.; Anti-communist movements -- United States.; Nationalism -- Soviet Union.; Communist countries.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Memorabilia.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Congressional records.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lev E. Dobriansky, 1970-1982.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Feb - Mar 1973 (Box 1)
    Dr. Dobriansky was a plaintiff in a 1973 lawsuit by the ACLU to access papers dating from 1946-1947 about Forcible Repatriation of Displaced Soviet Citizens – Operation Keelhaul. Citing the Freedom of Information Act, Dr. Dobriansky’s co-plaintiffs were Dr. Bertram D. Wolfe and Dr. Julius Epstein.
  - American Council for World Freedom (ACWF)
    - International Digest, 1977-1978; 4 issues (Box 1)
      Bi-monthly publication from the ACWF.
    - Newsletter, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      Newsletter for members. Includes descriptions of affiliates’ activities, some book reviews, and submissions from individuals.
    - Press releases, 1975-1977; 8 press releases (Box 1)
      Author names are Lee Edwards (secretary, ACWF), John D. Husband, Fred Schlafly (President, ACWF), Joan Sweetland. Cited are Arthur J. Goldberg (American Ambassador, Belgrade) and Lev E. Dobriansky.
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
      Summary of Publications Meeting. Pamphlet from 1974 WACL conference of Fred Schlafly’s speech. Information from 1975 ACWF conference.
  - Americanism Educational League, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    Reprint of 1974 article by John G. Schmitz, “Aiding our enemy- A suicidal policy.” Reprint of 1975 article and printed pamphlet by Lev E. Dobriansky, “The New Captive Nations.” Letter from Dobriansky to Edward S. Rankin, Executive Director.
  - Americans for Freedom of Captive Nations, 1971; 3 publications (Box 1)
    One of the participating chapters in the NCNC. Based in Los Angeles, California.
  - Annunzio, Frank, 1965-1976 (Box 1)
    Representative from Illinois. Includes resolutions, Congressional Records and correspondence.
  - Asian People’s Anti-Communist League (APACL), 1965-1975 (Box 1)
    See also World Anti-Communist League (WACL) and Ku Cheng-kang.
    The APACL gave rise to the WACL in 1966. Dr. Ku was the president of the APACL chapter of the Republic of China (in Taipei). Includes correspondence and joint communiques from the 19th and 21st conferences.
  - Asian representatives’ luncheon 4/2/1969 (Box 1)
    See also World Anti-Communist League (WACL).
    The NCNC sponsored a luncheon honoring Asian Representatives from the World Anti-Communist League and the Korean Freedom Center. The guests included: Admiral Sohn Won II, Dr. Phan Huy Quat, Dr. Jose M. Hernandez. Folder includes an invitation, correspondence, newspaper clippings, an NCNC press release and a guest list.
  - Captive Nations Week
    - 1960, May 1960 - Jul 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961
      - Congressional Record, Jul 1961; 4 identical sets (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Feb 1961 - Jul 1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962, Jun - Aug 1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963, Mar - Aug 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964
      - Congressional Record, Jun - Aug 1964 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Mar - Jul 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965
      - Congressional Record, Jul - Sep 1965 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Mar - Jul 1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966, Jan - Sep 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967
      - Congressional Record, Jul - Sep 1967 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Dec 1966 - Sep 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968
      - Congressional Record, Jul - Sep 1968 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, May - Aug 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1969
      - Congressional Record, Jul - Sep 1969 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Feb - Nov 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970
      - Congressional Record, Apr - Dec 1970 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Feb - Aug 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971
      - Congressional Record, May - Oct 1971 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Feb - Oct 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972
      - Congressional Record, Jun- Oct 1972 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Apr - Nov 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1973, Feb - Oct 1973 (Box 3)
      Includes a folder of photographs of Rep. Jack Kemp's visit to China for Captive Nations.
    - 1974
      - Congressional Record, Jun - Aug 1974 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, Mar - Oct 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1975
      - Congressional Record, Jun - Dec 1975 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, Mar - Sep 1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976, Jan - Sep 1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977, May - Aug 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978, Apr - Aug 1978 (Box 3)
      Includes a particularly large number of newspaper clippings.
    - 1979
      - Congressional Record, May - Nov 1979 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, Mar - Sep 1979 (Box 4)
    - 1980, Apr - Jul 1980 (Box 4)
    - 1981, Mar - Aug 1981 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, May 1960 - Jan 1979 (Box 4)
  - Committee for a Free China, 1975 (Box 4)
    Summary of annual meeting, November 1975, and two follow up letters from Lee Edwards, Secretary, about the meeting.
  - Conference programs, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    Includes: Human Rights After Helsinki (5/19/1977), The United States and China After Mao (11/30/1976), The U.S. and the USSR After Détente (1/27/1977), and an unnamed, undated draft program for a conference with emphasis on Asia.
  - Derwinski, Edward J., 1964-1974 (Box 4)
    Representative from Illinois. Includes Congressional Records, resolutions, correspondence and a news release.
  - Dobriansky, Lev E.
    - Correspondence A-G, 1960-1981 (Box 4)
      See Also Ukrainian Congress Committee of America (UCCA).
      Includes the following correspondence: Copies of mass distributed letters to Congressmen and Senators. Ali Akish, Idel-Ural Independence Committee; O.K. Armstrong, Missouri; Stephen T. Aucock; LeMar Baker, Tennessee; Frank E. Barnett, Department of Defense; Stephen Barrett Kanner; Sylvia Bernstein; Mario Biaggi, New York; Ihnat Billinsky, Philadelphia Captive Nations Committee; Richard Bolling; James J. Delaney; Ray J. Madden; George Brada; Benjamin Bradlee, Washington Post; John Buchanan; Patrick Buchanan; James L. Buckley, New York; Priscilla L. Buckley, National Review; Louis F. Budenz; Algirdas Budreckis, Assembly of Captive European Nations; Edgar C. Bundy, Church League of America; Paul H. Chellis, Constructive Councils of Georgia, Inc.; Chiang Kai-shek, Republic of China; Alois A. Chmela; Rouben Chublarian; Philip C. Clarke, American Security Council; Alan Courtney; Bernice Courtney, WIOD-Radio; Mrs. Richard J. Daley, Chicago; Sam P. Daniel, Jr.; Carolyn A. Davis, George Arents Research Library; Thomas J. Dodd; Harold Driver; David Dunn; Timothy Duskin; Edward L.R. Elson, Chaplain of the United States Senate; Lawrence E. Foust; John M. Fisher, American Security Council; Fr. Alexis, U. Floridi, S.J., SS. Peter and Paul Church of Ludlow, MA; Hiram L. Fong, Hawaii; J. W. Fulbright, Committee on Foreign Relations; William J. Gill; Arthur J. Goldberg, American Embassy in Belgrade, Yugoslavia; Charles E. Goodell, New York; David D. Goodwin; Philip Guarino; Don F. Guier, Oklahoma Civil Defense Agency.
    - Correspondence H-N, 1960-1981 (Box 4)
      Includes the following correspondence: George Haessler; Han Lih-wu, Institute of International Relations; Robert H. Hansen, Supreme Court; Billy James Hargis, Christian Crusade; S. I. Hayakawa; Jose Ma. Hernandez, Freedom Center, Seoul, South Korea; Harvey J. Hockstein; Herbert Hoover; Marvin Howell, Sacramento City College Library; Hen-chao Hsieh, Foreign Relations Committee, Legislative Yuan, Taiwan; Hsieh Jen-chao; Henry Lane Hull; Hubert H. Humphrey; Hungarian Freedom Fighters Federation Incorporated of USA and Canada; Henry M. Jackson; Raymond J. de Jaegher; Mrs. C. B. Johnson, Mothers’ Crusade for Victory over Communism; Walter H. Judd; Valentine Kalynyk, Americans to Free Captive Nations, Inc.; Myong Whai Kim; David S. King; Lane Kirkland, American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO); Thomas H. Knorr; Edward I. Koch, New York; Walther A. Kollacks, German-American National Congress, Inc.; Voldimars Korsts, National Republican Heritage Groups ( Nationalities) Council; Mrs. Michael Kowansky, Ladies Auxiliary Catholic War Veterans of the United States; Anthony Kubek, General C. L. Chennault Library, Troy State University; Henry J. Lacour, Jr.; General Thomas A. Lane; Ray Lapics, KACE Radio, Inc.; Frank J. Lausche; David Lawrence; Ernest S. Lee, AFL-CIO; Jay Lovestone, AFL-CIO; Joseph Lesawyer, Ukrainian National Association; Colonel Juan A. Lezana, Uruguay; Marvin Liebman, the Committee of One Million; Ivan Matteo Lombardo; Russell B. Long; Committee on Finance, U.S. Senate; Taras M. Lukach; Beatrice Mabry; Ray J. Madden; Daniel Marchishin, Captive Nations Committee of New Jersey; George Mardikian; John M. Martin, Jr., Committee on Ways and Means; Stephen May; James A. McClure; John W. McCormack, Speaker of the House; Gary E. McCuen, Greenhaven Press, Inc.; Tom McNamee; George Meany, AFL-CIO; Mr. and Mrs. Harry Metrinko; Metod M. Milac, Syracuse University Library; William E. Miller; Philip F. Mooney, Syracuse University Library; Thomas E. Morgan, Committee on Foreign Affairs; RAdm. William C. Mott, USN.
    - Correspondence O-Z, 1960-1981 (Box 4)
      Includes the following correspondence: Patrick Cardinal O’Boyle; A. Olechnik, Byelorussian Liberation Front; Too Chin Paik, National Assembly, Seoul, South Korea; Drew Pearson; Mrs. C. Peck; Pope John Paul II; Roman Rakhmanny; John R. Rarick; Henry Regnery; Kenneth D. Robertson; Nelson A. Rockefeller, New York; Edward J. Rozek, University of Colorado; Victor Rud; Anna Russell; General Dwight D. Eisenhower; Howland H. Sergeant, Radio Liberty Committee; Glenn A. Savage; Richard M. Scaife, the Carthage Foundation; R. K. Scott, America’s Future, Inc.; William W. Scranton; James C.H. Shen, Embassy of the Republic of China; Juhan Simonson, New Jersey Council of Estonian, Latvian and Lithuanian Americans; Askold Skalsky; Admiral Sohn Won Yil, Korean Anti-Communist League; George Sokolsky; John Sparkman; Mrs. Arnolds Spekke; William B. Spong, Jr., Committee on Public Works; Peter M. Stark; Slava Stetsko, Antibolshevik Bloc of Nations; Ted Stevens; Geoffrey Stewart-Smith, House of Commons; Chaowas Sudlabha, the Free People League of Thailand; Orest Szczudluk; Tran Van Chuong, Embassy of Vietnam; Jacques Trebile; Walter Trohan; Harry S. Truman; Earle W. Tuttle, The Truth; Cyrus Vance, U.S. Department of State; Lee N. Vogel, WQAM Radio; Patrick Walsh, Freedom Council of Canada; John C. Wetzel, America’s Future, Inc.; General Frederick Weyand; James E. Whitmire; Wu Chen-Tsai, China Forum; Clement J. Zablocki; Ardeshir Zahedi, Embassy of Iran; Anthony Zukowsky, Ukrainian Congress Committee of America.
    - Publications and statements, 1965-1979 (Box 4-5)
      Includes two books (in Box 4): The Vulnerable Russians and U.S.A. and the Soviet Myth. In Box 5, the folder includes: Reprints from the Ukrainian Quaterly: "Outstanding U.S. Myths on the Captive Nations;" "Ten Reasons Against the US-USSR Consular Treaty;" "The Traditional Captive Nations Week: Red Nightmare, Freedom’s Hope;" "Old Myths, New Realities about Russia: Freedom through understanding;" "A U.S. Policy of Unfinished Liberation;" "Review of U.S. Policy toward the USSR: A major theme for the 1967 Captive Nations Week;" "From Moscow’s Izvestia to Washington’s Post;" "Ten Years of Captive Nations Week." Hearing before the Committee on Foreign Relations for the Nomination of James Russell Wiggins. Statement before the Committee on Resolutions, 1964 Republican National Convention. WTOP Radio flier: Dobriansky Discusses Consular Convention. Washington Report: "Forget the Captive Nations?" The Best of The New Guard, 1961-1971: "Why Captive Nations Week?" New Guard: Book review of USA and the Soviet Myth. Devin-Adair Catalog: USA and the Soviet Myth. 2 copies of Testimony for the Republican National Convention, 1972: "Republicans consistently support the captive nations 1952 – 1972." Testimony before the Committee on Internal Security, U.S. House of Representatives, 1973. Pamphlet: Illusions of Détente. Program for public conference, Détente and the Future of the Middle East, Institute for Soviet and East European Studies: Economic Aspects of Détente. Testimony before the Subcomittee on Europe, Committee on Foreign Affairs, U.S. House of Representatives: Détente, Human Rights and the USSR. Memorandum for the Military Order of the World Wars: The Helsinki Accords, Slavery for Captive Nations? Clipping from The Rising Tide: "The New Captive Nations?" Pamphlet: The New Captive Nations. Commencement Address at Manor Junior College, Pa.: "Whose Shoes are you wearing?" Statement at Hearings on Genocide Convention, Committee on Foreign Relations, U.S. Senate. Vital Speeches of the Day, reprint of commencement address: "Whose shoes are you wearing?" Clipping from the National Review: "Another Captive Nations Week." Clipping from the Indianapolis Star: "Who’s next?"
  - Flood, Daniel J., 1965-1975 (Box 5)
    See also Resolutions 211 (1961), 14 (1965) and 106 (1973).
    Representative from Pennsylvania. Includes resolutions and correspondence, particularly letters from other political figures to whom Flood sent official bound copies of The Captive Nations Week Resolution.
  - General correspondence, 1962-1980 (Box 5)
    Includes: letters to or from Vera A. Dowhan or Mrs. Colby Bowden, Secretaries of the NCNC; letters forwarded to NCNC or Dobriansky in c.c.; and other miscellaneous correspondence. Names include: Audrey G. Acker, Nicholas Adams, William F. Ainley, Ivan Bazarko, M. Declan Bransfield III, Christian Science Monitor, Marianne Patrice Clarke, D.P. Musin, Douglas Darby, Lynn Davis, Andrew Dropic, Russ Evans, Mati Koiva, Bob Steele, Henry Flood, Joseph C. Fomler, V. Grundmanis, The Free Press, Bryan J. Holzberg, Indiana University, J.K.Jamieson, Parvis Kazemi, F.M. Kirby, Audrey Kirchhoff, Morris Kominsky, Rudolph Ch. Krempl, Hassan Mohamed Kutbi, Joseph Lesawyer, Norman R. Matschikowski Jr., Donald L. Miller, Allene Nickell, A. Olechnik, Byelorussian Liberation Front, Rudolfs Peksen, Bill Poole, Margit Rohtla, William G. Savage, Anicetas Simutis, John Cobb Smith, Geoffrey Stewart-Smith, George Tong, Lee N. Vogel, William J. Volonte, The Washington Star.
  - Ku Cheng-kang, 1963-1981 (Box 5)
    Mostly correspondence with Dobriansky. Includes a copy of "Unity, Anti-Communism and Salvation of Asia," an address by Ku at the 21st APACL Conference.
  - Letterhead, 1959-1980 (Box 5)
    Examples of blank NCNC letterhead and envelopes.
  - Memorabilia, 1960-1980 (Box 5)
    Miscellaneous items: two blank postcards from the Crusade for Freedom with God against Communist, one blank postcard that reads "Security Conference! The Baltic Nations demand: Withdrawal of occupation army freedom self-determination," commemorative non-postal stamps for the captive nations, an invitation to a dinner honoring the visit of 17 congressmen from Vietnam, a program with menu lfor the 1973 Day of Hope Dinner featuring Reverend Sun Myung Moon and Um Sim, Ambassador of the Khmer Republic. Additionally there is an undated 8x10 photograph of Dr. Lev E. Dobriansky, Danielf J. Flood, Rev. Dr. Chas W. Lowry, and Edward J. Derwinski.
  - Nanuashvili, Jan V., 1970-1975 (Box 5)
    Georgian émigré. Includes correspondence with Dobriansky and a review of his book, What Everyone in the Free World Should Know About Russia.
  - National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1972-1977 (Box 5)
    Includes Resolutions for Approval from 1972 and a news release from 1977.
  - News releases, 1962-1980 (Box 5)
    NCNC news releases, press releases, reports and memoranda. Includes: U.S. falls into propaganda trap (1962); Captive Nations’ sponsors gird for fight against non-aggression pact (1963); Wheat for freedom, not for sale (1963); 30 senators, 156 congressmen now members of NCNC, Donald L. Miller appointed Executive Director (1963); Consular convention with USSR scored as president asked to support captive nations unit (1964); Fulbright urged to hold open and frank hearings on consular convention (1965); Memorandum III (1965); Russian invasion of Czecho-Slovakia seen as proof for revamped U.S. policy (1968); 2 copies of Testimony for the Republican National Convention, 1972: Republicans consistently support the captive nations 1952 – 1972 (1972); 3 copies of McGovern no lover of captive nations (1972); NCNC report for ’72 (1972); 2 copies of The mistake was political, not ideational (1976); NCNC report for 1973 (1973); 2 copies of Afghanistan declared a captive nation (1980).